Guide to the George P. Hall & Son Photograph Collection [1876-1914] PR 24
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
George P. Hall & Son Photograph Collection
[1876-1914]
PR 24
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
63.1 Linear feet (52 boxes and 2 volumes)
Large-format views in this collection provide detailed, flattering depictions of Manhattan from the 1880s through the 1910s. Included are depictions of early skyscrapers, hotel and theater exteriors, harbor activity, and downtown streets, as well as views of Brooklyn's business areas and resorts. Views of the U.S. Navy's new steel battleships of the 1890s and areas outside New York are included. Note that the images in this collection have been digitized and can be viewed here.
Provenance
Approximately 2000 vintage negatives from the collection of James S. Hall were purchased on June 20, 1945. The indexes are presumed to have been produced by the George P. Hall & Son firm and were probably donated with the collection. Modern prints were produced between 1968 and 1975 by commercial studios under contract with the New-York Historical Society in an effort to reformat the oversize glass negatives within this collection. Between 1968 and 1972 contact prints were produced by Klein Brothers Studio, New York; between 1974 and 1975 photographic prints were produced by Wometco Photographic Services, Inc., New York, and in 1975, photographic prints were produced by Compo Photocolor, New York. After printing, most of the negatives were destroyed. An additional 103 photographic prints were provided by the International Museum of Photography at George Eastman House in about 1977 from negatives donated to them by the New-York Historical Society. In 2010, an additional 39 glass plate negatives were donated by Dolores Ballaster.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to ten exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Historical Note
The commercial photography firm George P. Hall & Son operated in Manhattan from 1886 through 1914. Working out of several studios, the firm documented the changing face of New York City at the turn of the 20th century. Hall & Son's photographs were available for general sale, were published in their own calendars and souvenir viewbooks, and appeared as illustrations in such publications as King's Views of New York, Staley's Views of New York, and Harper's Weekly.
George P. Hall (1832-1900) was born in 1832 in Troy, Ohio, and began his career in 1854 as a daguerreotypist in Dayton, Ohio. A year later he opened his first gallery in Indianapolis and then worked in St. Louis, before finally making his way to New York around 1872. He started his commercial photography business at 78 Fulton Street around 1875, and was officially joined by his son James S. Hall in 1886 when firm took the name George P. Hall & Son. The father and son operated the company until 1900, when George P. Hall died. James S. Hall continued to run the business until about 1914. A brief note in the Business Troubles column of the New York Times for June 4, 1914 indicates that creditors were filing a petition against Hall, and that he admitted his insolvency. It is presumed that the firm closed in the wake of these financial difficulties.
The Halls operated several studios in Manhattan. City directories published by Trow indicate that George P. Hall maintained a studio at 78 Fulton Street from 1876 to 1883. He moved his business to 157 Fulton Street in 1883, where he was joined by his son; that studio remained open until 1901. Later shops included those at 303 Broadway from 1890 to 1894, at 52 Water Street from 1897 to 1902, at 212 Broadway from 1901 to 1914, at 364 Bowery from 1902 to 1903, and at 230 Grand Street from 1903 to 1904. The Halls made their residences in Brooklyn, and often turned their cameras toward features of that city as well as Manhattan. They also worked as marine and engineering photographers.
Scope and Content Note
The George P. Hall & Son Photograph Collection spans the period from 1876 through 1914 and consists of vintage glass negatives, vintage photographic logbooks, and modern photographic contact prints printed from 1965 to 1975 from Hall & Son's original oversize glass negatives. The collection is arranged into six series: Photographs of Manhattan; Photographs of Brooklyn, The Bronx, Queens, and Staten Island; Photographs Outside New York City; Photographs by Subject; Negatives; and Logbooks. Within each photographic subseries, photographs are divided into unmounted and mounted to accommodate preservation needs.
The large-format views in this collection provide clear, extremely detailed and flattering depictions of a variety of subjects, including Manhattan's early skyscrapers, hotels and theater exteriors, harbor activity, and downtown streets, as well as Brooklyn's business areas and resorts. George P. Hall & Son photographed the Battery skyline repeatedly from the 1880s to the 1910s, documenting the dramatic changes that occurred as New York progressed from a lowrise to a highrise city. Many of Hall & Son's views are notable for their high-angle perspectives. Like many commercial photographers of the time, Hall & Son focused on the highlights of New York; the newest skyscrapers, the record-breaking bridges, and the most popular theaters and attractions. Views in this collection also depict many of the United States Navy's new steel battleships of the 1890s. Also included are some views of the Hall's business premises and family members. Hall & Son primarily documented building exteriors; when interior views are available, this has been noted in the finding aid.
The photographic prints in this collection were made between 1965 and 1975 from George P. Hall & Son's original glass plate negatives ranging in size from 11 x 14 to 11 x 18 to 14 x 17 inches. The majority of the original negatives from which these prints were created have been destroyed. The prints produced between 1965 and 1970 by Klein Brothers are unmounted prints with a matte finish; these show a greater variety of tone than the later high-contrast, glossy prints produced by Compo Photocolor, The International Museum of Photography at George Eastman House, and Wometco Photographic Services, which are mounted on paper board.
Some photographs bear brief descriptive captions, dates and negative numbers handwritten in block lettering on the original negatives and printed into the photographs. The majority of the photographs have been captioned on the verso by N-YHS staff; some of these descriptions correspond to those from the original negative sleeves, but many have been assigned progressively as staff members have researched photographs over the years. Some photographs have been given more detailed descriptions than others, reflecting this individual research.
Researchers should be aware that oversize negatives from a variety of other collections belonging to The New-York Historical Society were once integrated into the Hall Collection. While efforts were made during processing to separate out all materials that could be readily attributed to other photographers, some unmarked photographs within this collection may not be the work of George P. Hall & Son. Attributions of these photographs should be made with caution.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Photographs of Manhattan
Series II: Photographs of Brooklyn, The Bronx, Queens, and Staten Island
Series III: Photographs Outside New York
Series IV: Photographs by Subject
Series V: Negatives
Series VI: Logbooks
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Other vintage photographic prints by George P. Hall & Son from a variety of sources can be found in the Geographic File (PR 020) and in the George B. Post Architectural Record Collection (PR 053) in the New-York Historical Society's Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections. The Calendar Collection (PR 146) includes George P. Hall & Son's 1907 Calendar, New York Historic & Picturesque. The Album File contains an album (PR 002-208) of photographs by George P. Hall & Son entitled Central Bridge over the Harlem River, New York City, and approaches thereto.
The International Museum of Photography at the George Eastman House owns 103 glass negatives by George P. Hall & Son that were originally part of this collection of negatives; modern photographic prints from these negatives are available within this collection. The Museum of the City of New York and the New York Public Library also own photographs by George P. Hall & Son.
Hall family; Hall, George P. -- Family; Hall, George P., 1832-1900; Hall, James S.; Bridges -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cityscapes; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Contact prints; Glass negatives; Historic buildings -- New York (State); Hotels -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Logbooks; Long Island (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Negatives; New York (N.Y.); Office buildings -- New York (State); Parks -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Photographic prints; Restaurants -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Ships; Skylines; Skyscrapers -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.); Streets -- New York (State); Theaters -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Warships
- Series I: Photographs of Manhattan
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I is the largest of the photographic series, with approximately 850 modern silver gelatin prints. It is arranged into ten subseries by subject: Bridges and River Views; Churches and Temples; Cityscapes and Panoramas; Commercial Buildings; Hotels; Public Buildings and Institutions; Residences; Restaurants; Statues and Monuments; and Theaters. Each subseries is divided into mounted and unmounted. The views collectively document much of Manhattan, with a particular emphasis on major institutions, tourist attractions, waterfronts and bridges, and business districts. For convenience, this series includes photographs of popular tourist sites on the smaller, non-borough islands surrounding Manhattan; these include views of the Statue of Liberty, the Ellis Island Immigration Station, and Castle William on Governor's Island.
  The Halls sometimes worked as marine photographers, and more generally turned their cameras toward the rivers, harbors, and bridges surrounding New York City. The Bridges and River Views subseries includes flattering views of the waterways of New York, including everything from iconic images of foot traffic on the Brooklyn Bridge to views of the three southern East River bridges. Many views encompass the rapidly changing New York skyline taken from the surrounding waterways.
  The Churches and Temples subseries includes a variety exterior views of the oldest and most notable religious institutions in the city, including Trinity Church, St. Paul's Chapel, the Cathedral of St. John the Divine [Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine], and Temple Beth-El. Cityscapes and Panoramas includes views of the changing Manhattan skyline from a variety of vantage points. Hall & Son frequented the roofs of tall buildings to capture the city from a dramatic overhead angle.
  Commercial Buildings includes views of a variety of buildings, from banks to department stores, such as Saks & Co. at its original Herald Square location, to such dramatic New York newcomers as the Flatiron (Fuller) Building during and after construction. Photographs in this subseries are mostly straightforward portraits of individual buildings; many of the same structures can be found within broader settings in the Street Scenes subseries. Photographs in the Hotels subseries are similar in nature to those of commercial buildings, primarily focusing on large elegant midtown hotels.
  Public Buildings and Institutions contains views of many famous New York institutions, including a variety of views of Columbia University and Barnard College, City Hall, Federal Hall, and Tammany Hall. Photographs of the interior of Pennsylvania Station from the 1910s and of the excavation site before its construction are available in this series. Also included are views of several hospitals, museums (including The New-York Historical Society in 1907) and transportation centers.
  Residences depicted include the Jumel Mansion and the Tiffany Mansion, as well as unidentified brownstones and Gramercy Square residences. Restaurants holds only a few images, including Delmonico's and the Metropolitan Club's interior with a banquet set for Mayor Seth Low. Statues and Monuments includes such notables as Grant's Tomb, the Statue of Liberty, and Washington Arch as well as smaller statuary.
  Street Scenes is the largest subseries and provides rich documentation of the city. Buildings, street life, and transportation means are depicted with great detail. The subseries is arranged into three categories: Named Streets, Numbered Avenues, and Numbered Streets. Within these categories, photographs are arranged alphabetically, then by ascending address (for example, note that Broadway and Fifth Avenue sections of street scenes are arranged from south to north). This series also includes views of several of the popular squares and smaller parks in the city, including many photographs of Union Square and City Hall Park. Views of Broadway from its southern extremity at Bowling Green to 145th Street are available, as are photographs of the maritime businesses along South Street. Views of many of George P. Hall & Son's business premises are included within this series. A few photographs in this series show a slightly darker side of Manhattan living, such as the depiction of slum buildings along Chrystie Street. Occasional copy work is included, such as a copy of "Broadway, north from Bond Street," by Mathew Brady from 1867.
  Theaters depicted include many of the popular venues of the first decade of the 1900s. Included within this category are views of Madison Square Garden (including a few interior views of exhibits), the Belasco Theatre, the Hippodrome, and the Harlem Opera House.
  - Bridges and River Views - Unmounted
    - Brooklyn Bridge (7), [1890-1900], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - East River (2), 1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - High Bridge (2), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Macomb's Dam Bridge [Central Bridge], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Manhattan Bridge, 1 including Ferry Terminal (2), [1910] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - New York Harbor (2), 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Queensboro Bridge, [1910-1914], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Third Avenue Bridge, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Washington Bridge, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Williamsburg Bridge, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified Harlem River bridge, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bridges and River Views - Mounted
    - Brooklyn Bridge (15), [1900-1908], undated (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
    - East River views (4), [1910], undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - East River views with Manhattan skyline (8), 1903-1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
    - East River showing three bridges: Brooklyn, Manhattan and Williamsburg (7), 1908-1912, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
    - Hudson River views with Manhattan skyline (14), [1900-1914], undated (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
    - Hudson River views with midtown Manhattan (2), [1909] (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Hudson River views with Palisades and upper Manhattan (2), [1902], undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Hudson River views - piers, [1905-1909], undated (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Manhattan Bridge, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - New York Harbor panorama (4), [1904] (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - New York Harbor with Castle Garden, includes the General Slocum [steamboat](3), [1905], undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - New York Harbor with Manhattan skyline (7), 1900-1912, undated (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
    - Queensboro Bridge, including construction (7), [1906]-1910, undated (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
    - Riverside Viaduct panorama (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Third Avenue Bridge (2), [1905-1910] (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Williamsburg Bridge (10), [1903]-1910 (Box 4, Folder 34-36)
    - Willis Avenue Railroad Bridge, [1900] (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Churches and Temples -- Unmounted
    - Bloomingdale Reformed Dutch Church, Mrs. George Henry Gilbert's funeral, 1904 Dec. (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Broadway Tabernacle, interiors (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Church of the Ascension, interior, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Church of Christ Scientist, First, exterior and interior (2), [1898] (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Church of Christ Scientist, Second (2), [1899]-1900 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Church of the Transfiguration [The Little Church Around the Corner] (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Fourth Avenue Presbyterian Church [Dr. Crosby's church], undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Grace Church, interiors and exteriors (7), 1909, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Holy Trinity [Dr. Ting's church], [1880] (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - St. Agnes Chapel, West 91st Street, [1900] (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. Bartholomew's, Madison Avenue and 44th Street, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. Francis Xavier, 16th Street at Fifth Avenue, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. James Lutheran, 73rd Street and Madison Avenue, [1904] (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. John's Chapel, Varick Street, interior and exterior (2), undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. Mark's in-the-Bowery, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. Patrick's Cathedral, interiors (3), undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. Paul's Chapel, copy photograph of an engraving of interior, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - St. Paul's Chapel, exteriors (4), undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - South Church, 38th Street and Madison Avenue, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Trinity Church (3), undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Unidentified church interiors (3), undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Churches and Temples - Mounted
    - Broadway Tabernacle, Broadway and 56th Street, [1910] (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Cathedral of St. John the Divine [Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine], undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - St. Patrick's Cathedral, Fifth Avenue and 50th Street (2), 1909 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - St. Paul's Chapel, 1 includes Rev. Dr. Kemp and choir in front of churchyard portico (9), [1900]-1908 (Box 5, Folder 43-44)
    - Temple Beth-El, Fifth Avenue and 76th Street, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Trinity Church, Broadway and Wall Street, 1903-1910 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Cityscapes and Panoramas - Unmounted
    - Lower Manhattan (4), undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Midtown Manhattan (2), undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Upper Manhattan, from Bloomingdale Asylum (2), undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Cityscapes and Panoramas - Mounted
    - Lower Manhattan (10), [1900]-1905, undated (Box 6, Folder 47-49)
    - Midtown Manhattan (3), [1905]-1910, undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Commercial Buildings - Unmounted
    - Aeolian Hall, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Aldrich Court Building, 39-55 Broadway, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - American Bank Note Co., 70 Broad Street, [1910] (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Battery Park Building, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Broadway Central National Bank, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Chesebrough Building, State Street (3), 1899, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Cortland Hardware, 76 Cortland Street [Copy photograph of a watercolor, ca. 1910], undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Equitable Building, Broadway and Cedar Street, fire [copy photograph of a hand-colored photograph with painted flames], 1912 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Everett Building, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Exchange Court Building, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Fifth Avenue Building, Fifth Avenue and 23rd Street, [1909] (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Grace & Co., exterior and interior (2), undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Insurance Advocate, New and Liberty Streets, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - International Express Co., undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - International Silver Co., undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Liberty National Bank, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Market & Fulton National Bank, 81 Fulton Street, [1899] (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Mercantile National Bank, Broadway (2), undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - J.P. Morgan Building, Wall and Broad Streets, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Mutual Reserve Life INsurance co., Broadway and Duane Street [copy of an artist's rendering], undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Nassau Bank, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - National Park Bank of New York, 214 Broadway, interior (2), [1910], undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - New York Produce Exchange, interior, [1890]-1896 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - New York Savings Bank, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Old Beekman, Gold Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Post [ Evening Post], interiors (7), undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Pulitzer Building [World Building], 1909 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Quintard Iron Works, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Redmond & Co., 33 Wall Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Saks & Co., 34th Street and Sixth Avenue, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - G. Sidenberg & Co., undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Title Guarantee & Trust Co., 176 Broadway, [1909] (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Trinity Building, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Wells Fargo & Co., undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Western Electric Co., undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Western Union Building, exterior and interior (2), undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Windsor Arcade, Fifth Avenue at 46th Street (2), undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Young Bros. & Boss Co., interior of Scenic Studios, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Commercial Buildings - Mounted
    - American Surety Building, 3 Pine Street, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Bankers Trust Co. Building, Nassau and Wall Streets (3), 1912 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Baudouine Building, 1187 Broadway and 28th Street, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Butterick Building, Spring and MacDougal Streets, undated (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Central Building [Central Railroad of New Jersey], West and Liberty Streets, undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - City Investing Building, Broadway, Cortlandt and Church Streets [Copy photograph of drawing], [1908] (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Commercial Building, Broad and Beaver Streets, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Commercial Cable Building, Broad Street (2), undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Corn Exchange Bank, 11-19 William Street, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Edison Building, [1910] (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Emigrant Industrial Savings Bank, undated (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Empire Building, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Fidelity Casualty Co., between Liberty and Cedar on Church Street, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Flatiron [Fuller] Building, during construction, [1902-1903] (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Flatiron [Fuller] Building, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Hanover National Bank, Pine and Nassau Streets, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Home Life Insurance Co., 253 Broadway (2), [1904], 1910 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Hudson Terminal Building, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Liverpool and London Insurance Co. Building, 45 William Street, undated (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Manhattan Life Insurance Co. Building (2), [1905], undated (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Manhattan Refrigerating Co., West Street, undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Maritime Exchange [copy of rendering by Robert Kendrick], [1903] (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance Co., interior, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Mills Building, ornamental iron gate, Broad Street, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 63)